her name is francis haugen that is a fact that  facebook has been anxious to know since last month
when an anonymous former employee filed complaints  with federal law enforcement the complaints say
facebook's own research shows that it amplifies  hate misinformation and political unrest but the
company hides what it knows one complaint alleges  that facebook's instagram harms teenage girls
what makes haugen's complaints unprecedented is  the trove of private facebook research she took
when she quit in may the documents appeared first  last month in the wall street journal but tonight
frances haugen is revealing her identity to  explain why she became the facebook whistleblower
the story will continue in a moment
the thing i saw at facebook over and over again  was there were conflicts of interest between what
was good for the public and what was good for  facebook and facebook over and over again chose
to optimize for its own interests like making more  money francis haugen is 37 a data scientist from
iowa with a degree in computer engineering and a  harvard master's degree in business for 15 years
she's worked for companies including google and  pinterest i've seen a bunch of social networks
and it was substantially worse at facebook than  anything i'd seen before you know someone else
might have just quit and moved on and i wonder why  you take this stand imagine you know what's going
on inside facebook and you know no one on the  outside knows i knew what my future looked like
if i continued to stay inside of facebook which is  person after person after person has tackled this
inside of facebook and ground themselves to the  ground when and how did it occur to you to take
all of these documents out of the company at some  point in 2021 i realized okay i'm going to have
to do this in a systemic way and i have to get out  enough that no one can question that this is real
she secretly copied tens of thousands  of pages of facebook internal research
she says evidence shows that the company is lying  to the public about making significant progress
against hate violence and misinformation one study  she found from this year says we estimate that we
may action as little as three to five percent  of hate and about six tenths of one percent of
violence and incitement on facebook despite  being the best in the world at it to quote
from another one of the documents you brought  out we have evidence from a variety of sources
that hate speech divisive political speech and  misinformation on facebook and the family of apps
are affecting societies around the world when  we live in an information environment that is
full of angry hateful polarizing content it erodes  our civic trust it erodes our faith in each other
it erodes our ability to want to care for each  other the version of facebook that exists today
is tearing our societies apart and  causing ethnic violence around the world
ethnic violence including myanmar in 2018 when  the military used facebook to launch a genocide
the first quarter of 2019. francis haugen told  us she was recruited by facebook in 2019 she
says she agreed to take the job only if she could  work against misinformation because she had lost
a friend to online conspiracy theories i never  wanted anyone to feel the pain that i had felt
and i had seen how high the stakes were in terms  of making sure there was high quality information
on facebook at headquarters she was assigned  to civic integrity which worked on risks to
elections including misinformation but after  this past election there was a turning point
they told us we're dissolving civic integrity  like they basically said oh good we made it
through the election there wasn't riots we can get  rid of civic integrity now fast forward a couple
months we got the insurrection and when they got  rid of civic integrity it was the moment where
i was like i don't trust that they're willing to  actually invest what needs to be invested to keep
facebook from being dangerous facebook says  the work of civic integrity was distributed to
other units haugen told us the root of facebook's  problem is in a change that it made in 2018 to its
algorithms the programming that decides  what you see on your facebook news feed
so you know you have your phone you might see  only 100 pieces of content if you sit and scroll
off for you know five minutes but facebook  has thousands of options it could show you
the algorithm picks from those options based on  the kind of content you've engaged with the most
in the past and one of the consequences of how  facebook is picking out that content today is it
is optimizing for content that gets engagement  or reaction but its own research is showing
that content that is hateful that is divisive that  is polarizing it's easier to inspire people to
anger than it is to other emotions misinformation  angry content is enticing to people and keeps
them on the platform yes facebook has realized  that if they change the algorithm to be safer
people will spend less time on the site they'll  click on less ads they'll make less money haugen
says facebook understood the danger to the 2020  election so it turned on safety systems to reduce
but many of those changes she says were  temporary and as soon as the election was
over they turned them back off or they changed  the settings back to what they were before
to prioritize growth over safety and that  really feels like a betrayal of democracy to me
facebook says some of the safety systems remained  but after the election facebook was used by some
to organize the january sixth insurrection  prosecutors cite facebook posts as evidence
photos of armed partisans and texts including  by bullet or ballot restoration of the republic
is coming extremists used many platforms but  facebook is a recurring theme after the attack
facebook employees raged on an internal message  board copied by haugen haven't we had enough
time to figure out how to manage discourse without  enabling violence we looked for positive comments
and found this i don't think our leadership  team ignores data ignores dissent ignores truth
but that drew this reply welcome to facebook  i see you just joined in november 2020
we have been watching wishy-washy actions  of company leadership for years now
colleagues cannot conscience working for a  company that does not do more to mitigate
the negative effects of its platform facebook  essentially amplifies the worst of human nature
it's one of these unfortunate consequences  right no one at facebook is malevolent but
the incentives are misaligned right like facebook  makes more money when you consume more content
people enjoy engaging with things that elicit an  emotional reaction and the more anger that they
get exposed to the more they interact and more  they consume that dynamic led to a complaint to
facebook by major political parties across europe  this 2019 internal report obtained by haugen
says that the parties feel strongly that the  change to the algorithm has forced them to skew
negative in their communications on facebook  leading them into more extreme policy positions
the european political parties were essentially  saying to facebook the way you've written
your algorithm is changing the way we lead our  countries yes you are forcing us to take positions
that we don't like that we know are bad for  society we know if we don't take those positions
we won't win in the marketplace of social media  evidence of harm she says extends to facebook's
instagram app one of the facebook internal studies  that you found talks about how instagram harms
teenage girls oh yeah one study says 13 and a  half percent of teen girls say instagram makes
thoughts of suicide worse 17 of teen girls say  instagram makes eating disorders worse and what's
super tragic is facebook's own research says as  these young women begin to consume this eating
disorder content they get more and more depressed  and it actually makes them use the app more
and so they end up in this feedback cycle  where they hate their bodies more and more
facebook's own research says it is not  just that instagram is dangerous for
teenagers that it harms teenagers it's that it is  distinctly worse than other forms of social media
facebook said just last week it would postpone  plans to create an instagram for younger children
last month haugen's lawyers filed at least  eight complaints with the securities and
exchange commission which enforces the law in  financial markets the complaints compare the
internal research with the company's public face  often that of ceo mark zuckerberg here testifying
remotely to congress last march we removed content  that could lead to imminent real world harm
we've built an unprecedented third-party  fact-checking program the system isn't perfect but
it's the best approach that we've found to address  misinformation in line with our country's values
one of francis haugen's lawyers is john tai he's  the founder of a washington legal group called
whistleblower aid what is the legal theory behind  going to the sec what laws are you alleging have
been broken as a publicly traded company facebook  is required to not lie to its investors or even
withhold material information so the  sec regularly brings enforcement actions
alleging that companies like facebook and others  are making material misstatements and omissions
that affect investors adversely one of the things  that facebook might allege is that she stole
company documents the dodd-frank act passed  over 10 years ago at this point created uh
an office of the whistleblower inside the sec and  one of the provisions of that law says that no
company can prohibit its employees from  from communicating with the sec and sharing
internal corporate documents with the  sec i have a lot of empathy for mark
and mark has never set out to make a hateful  platform but he has allowed choices to be made
where the side effects of those choices are that  hateful polarizing content gets more distribution
more reach facebook declined an interview but  in a written statement to 60 minutes it said
every day our teams have to balance protecting  the right of billions of people to express
themselves openly with the need to keep our  platform a safe and positive place we continue
to make significant improvements to tackle the  spread of misinformation and harmful content
to suggest we encourage bad content and do nothing  is just not true if any research had identified an
exact solution to these complex challenges  the tech industry governments and society
would have solved them a long time ago facebook  is a one trillion dollar company just 17 years
old it has 2.8 billion users which is 60 percent  of all internet connected people on earth francis
haugen plans to testify before congress this week  she believes the federal government should impose
regulations facebook has demonstrated they cannot  act independently facebook over and over again has
shown it uses profit over safety it is subsidizing  is paying for its profits with our safety
i'm hoping that this will have had a big  enough impact on the world that they get
the fortitude and the motivation to actually go  put those regulations into place that's my hope
more from the facebook whistleblower publishers
know you are more likely to engage with angry  content at 60minutesovertime.com by colaguard