in his first 100 days president biden focused on  the coronavirus pandemic but over the course of
his term the biden presidency will be defined  by how the united states competes with china
in a few years china's economy is expected  to surpass the u.s as the world's biggest
to determine how the united states will deal with  china's growing influence mr biden has chosen one
of his closest aides as secretary of state it  falls to anthony blinken to rebuild a depleted
and demoralized state department repair u.s  alliances and champion what diplomats call the
rules-based international order the written and  unwritten code that governs how nations deal with
one another rules that he says are now threatened  by china the story will continue in a moment
it is the one country in the world that has  the military economic diplomatic uh capacity to
undermine or challenge the rules-based order that  we uh we care so much about and are determined
to defend but i want to be very clear about  something and this is important our purpose is not
to contain china to hold it back to keep it  down it is to uphold this rules-based order
that china is posing a challenge to anyone who  poses a challenge to that order we're going to
stand up and defend it i know you say the goal is  not to contain china but have you ever seen china
be so assertive or aggressive militarily no we  haven't i think what we've witnessed over the last
several years is china acting more repressively at  home and more aggressively abroad that is a fact
what's china's goal i think that over time  china believes that it it can be and should
be and will be the dominant country in the world  chinese fighter jets are increasingly visible
in the skies above the western pacific  where the u.s navy also has a presence
this past week china's president xi unveiled  three new warships to patrol the south china sea
it already has the world's largest navy and could  use it to invade taiwan a democratic island and
long-standing u.s ally do you think we're heading  towards some sort of military confrontation with
china i think it's profoundly against the  interests of both china and the united states
uh to uh to get to that point or even to  head in that direction let's talk about human
rights describe what you see it's happening in  xinjiang that maybe the rest of the world doesn't
we've made clear that um we see a genocide having  taken place against uh the uyghurs in xinjiang
more than a million people have been put  into choose your term concentration camps
re-education camps internment camps when  beijing says oh there's a terrorism threat
which we don't see it's not coming from a million  people our administration six weeks ago in alaska
secretary blinken confronted young giache  china's top diplomat about genocide in xinjiang
and china's military aggression we feel an  obligation to raise these issues here today
the exchange became an international incident  caught on camera and not lost in translation
the united states does not have the qualification  to say that it wants to speak to china from a
position of strength if shinzone is in a red line  with china then what is look we don't have the
luxury of not dealing with china there are real  complexities to the relationship whether it's the
adversarial piece whether it's the competitive  piece whether it's the the cooperative piece
even before the meeting in alaska president  xi had warned about the dawn of a new cold war
during president trump's time in office  china found the u.s less predictable than
past administrations and i just announced another  10 tariffs mr trump imposed tariffs on hundreds
of billions of dollars of chinese products in  response to what he called unfair trade practices
and the theft of u.s intellectual property so far  the biden administration has kept the tariffs in
place i also told president xi that we'll maintain  a strong military presence china may be the only
big issue of the day in washington in which  democrats and republicans find common cause
the chinese have stolen hundreds of billions  if not trillions of dollars of trade secrets
and intellectual property from the united states  that sounds like the actions of an enemy certainly
sounds like the actions of of someone who's  trying to compete unfairly uh and increasingly in
adversarial ways but we're much more effective  and stronger when we're bringing like-minded
and similarly aggrieved countries together to say  to beijing this can't stand and it won't stand
so is that a message that president biden has  delivered to president xi certainly in their in
their first conversation uh they covered a lot  of ground it was a reportedly a two-hour phone
call it was yeah i was there and so did president  biden tell president xi to cut it out president
biden made clear that in a number of areas we have  real concerns about the actions that china has
taken and that includes in the economic area and  that includes the theft of intellectual property
china's gross domestic product is expected  to surpass the united states as early as 2028
well it's a large country it's got a lot of  people if china becomes the wealthiest country
in the world doesn't that also make it the most  powerful a lot depends on how it uses that wealth
it has an aging population it has significant  uh environmental problems and so on but here's
the way i think about it nor writ large if we're  talking about what really makes the wealth of a
nation fundamentally it's it's human resources and  the ability of any one country to maximize their
potential that's the challenge uh for us it's the  challenge for china i think we're in a much better
place to maximize that uh that human potential  than any country on earth if we're smart about it
china thinks long-term strategically decades  in advance is america just caught up on
the latest fires here and there and we're not  thinking long term strategically and as a result
china will surpass us what i  found looking at our own history
is that when we've confronted a significant  challenge significant competition uh significant
adversity we've managed to come together and  actually do the long-term thinking the long-term
investment and that is really the moment we're in  now and that's the test that i think we're facing
are we actually going to rise to  it president biden believes we are
anthony blinken occupies a suite of offices  on the seventh floor of the state department
but he first worked for joe biden at the senate  foreign relations committee nearly 20 years ago
and has barely left his side since in the obama  white house secretary blinken held concurrent
roles as an assistant to the president and the  national security advisor for vice president biden
it's been the most consequential professional  relationship and and also in many ways personal
relationship uh that i've uh that i've had how  often do you speak it's pretty close to daley you
speak to him every day in one way or another  you know we're we're pretty good at meetings
so there are a few of those when i thought  about the relationship that you have had
with with president biden over the years in  the senate and then when he was vice president
the only relationship that i could come up with  though i'm not a historian um was of course
secretary baker and president george h.w bush  i'd be flattered by any comparison to secretary
baker i actually i spoke to him on the phone a few  months ago and we talked about the importance of
ideally a secretary of state having a close  relationship with uh with the president
he was extraordinarily effective for all  sorts of reasons but that was i think a source
of his effectiveness secretary of state  james baker helped president george h.w bush
end the cold war with the soviet union the  current secretary is in the midst of winding
down america's longest war in afghanistan are you  prepared for a worst case scenario in afghanistan
where the u.s backed government fails  and the taliban takes over we have to
be prepared for every scenario and there are a  range of them and uh we we're looking at this
uh in a very clear-eyed way but nora we've  been engaged in afghanistan for 20 years and
we sometimes forget why we went there in the first  place and that was to deal with the people who
attacked us on 9 11. and we did just because our  troops are coming home doesn't mean we're leaving
we're not our embassy's staying the support that  we're giving to afghanistan when it comes to
economic support development humanitarian that  that remains and not only from us from partners
and allies somewhat related will the biden  administration close guantanamo bay we believe
that it should be that's certainly a goal but  it's something that we'll bring some focus to in
the months ahead in this past wednesday's address  to congress president biden spoke about his plans
for immigration reform for more than 30 years  politicians have talked about immigration reform
and we've done nothing about it it's time to fix  it it's a subject not usually central to the state
department's mission but we asked secretary  blinken about it because of the refugee crisis
on america's southern border border crossings  for undocumented immigrants have skyrocketed
in march more than a hundred and seventy thousand  people were taken into custody that's the highest
in 20 years are the policies of  the bidet administration to blame
no what we're seeing is indeed a surge of people  to the border we've seen that in the past but
we inherited a totally broken system uh broken  intentionally and it takes time to fix it and by
the way our message is very clear don't come the  border is not open you won't get in but we have to
understand what is motivating so many people to do  this and it is usually desperation but that's not
new i want to talk about the policies of the biden  administration because president biden did use his
executive authority to curb deportations to allow  more asylum seekers to enter the united states
so are these new policies by the administration  contributing to this surge we're focused when it
comes to people coming into making sure that that  children unaccompanied minors are treated humanely
and according to the law is it problematic  to tell migrants well no you can't come here
and then at the same time create a different  situation on the ground that does allow them
to come but the point is that they're not and  what's one of the challenges that uh that we've
had is that um traffickers and others are trying  to tell them that the border is open it's not but
children are being allowed in and they're being  children are the one exception because we we will
not it is the it is the right thing to do we are  not going to abide the notion that children are
kept in a precarious dangerous situation that is  unacceptable blinken himself is a father of two
young children and hails from a family that only  a few generations ago were themselves refugees his
paternal great grandfather meyer blinken emigrated  to new york city from ukraine fleeing russian
oppression in 1904 this coming week the secretary  of state will visit ukraine to show support for
the country currently in the throes of more recent  russian aggression president putin has amassed a
very large force at the border with ukraine more  than a hundred thousand troops what is putin up to
you're right there are more forces massed on  the border with ukraine than any time since
2014 when russia actually invaded i can't  tell you that we know mr putin's intentions
there are any number of things that he could  do or or choose not to do what we have seen in
the last few days is apparently a decision to  pull back some of those forces and we've seen some
of them in fact start to pull back that's been  verified that they are pulling back starting now
we're watching that very very carefully
secretary blinken on china's  influence in hong kong
i think there'll be an economic  blow back at 60 minutesovertime.com