when yuval noah harari published his first  book sapiens in 2014 about the history of the
human species it became a global bestseller in  turn the little-known israeli history professor
into one of the most popular  writers and thinkers on the planet
but when we met with harari in tel aviv this  summer it wasn't our species past that concerned
him it was our future harare believes we may be  on the brink of creating not just a new enhanced
species of human but an entirely new kind of  being one that's far more intelligent than we are
it sounds like science fiction but  you've all know a harare says it's
actually much more dangerous than that  the story will continue in a moment
you said we are one of the last generations of  homo sapiens within a century or two earth will be
dominated by entities that are more different from  us than we are different from chimpanzees yeah
what the hell does that mean that freaked  me out you know we'll soon have the power
to re-engineer our bodies and brains whether it is  with genetic engineering or by directly connecting
brains to computers or by creating  completely non-organic entities
artificial intelligence which is not based at  all on the organic body and the organic brain
and these technologies are developing at  breakneck speed if that is true then it
creates a whole other species this is something  which is way beyond just another species you all
know a harare is talking about the race to  develop artificial intelligence as well as
other technologies like gene editing that could  one day enable parents to create smarter or more
attractive children and brain computer interfaces  that could result in human machine hybrids
what does that do to a society i mean it  seems like the rich will have access whereas
others wouldn't one of the dangers is that we  will see in the coming decades a process of
greater inequality than in any previous time  in history because for the first time it will
be real biological inequality if the new  technologies are available only to the rich
or only to people from a certain country  then homo sapiens will split into different
biological costs because they really have  different bodies and different abilities
ferrari has spent the last few years lecturing  and writing about what may lie ahead for humankind
in the coming generations we will learn how  to engineer bodies and brains and minds he's
written two books about the challenges we face in  the future homo deus and 21 lessons for the 21st
century which along with sapiens have sold more  than 35 million copies and been translated into
65 languages his writings have been recommended  by president barack obama as well as tech moguls
bill gates and mark zuckerberg you raise warnings  about technology you're also embraced by a lot of
folks in silicon valley yeah isn't that sort of  a contradiction they are a bit afraid of their
own power that they have realized the immense  influence they have over the world over the
course of evolution really and i think that spooks  at least some of them and that's a good thing
um and this is why they are kind of to some  extent open to listening you started as a
history professor what do you call yourself now  i'm still a historian but i think history is the
study of change not just the study of the past  but it covers the future as well harari got his
phd in history at oxford and lives in israel  where the past is still very present he took
us to this archaeological site called tel gezer  four five thousand years ago this was one of the
biggest cities in the area harare says cities  like this were only possible because about 70
000 years ago our species homo sapiens experienced  a cognitive change that helped us create language
which then made it possible for us to cooperate in  large groups and drive neanderthals and all other
less cooperative human species into extinction  harare fears we are now the ones at risk of
being dominated by artificial intelligence maybe  the biggest thing that we are facing is really
a kind of evolutionary divergence for millions of  years intelligence and consciousness went together
consciousness is the ability to feel things  like pain and pleasure and love and hate
intelligence is the ability to solve problems  but computers or artificial intelligence
they don't have consciousness they just have  intelligence they solve problems in a completely
different way than us now in science fiction  it's often assumed that as computers will become
more and more intelligent they will inevitably  also gain consciousness but actually it's much
more frightening than that in a way they will be  able to solve more and more problems better than
us without having any consciousness any feelings  and they will have power over us they are already
gaining power over us some lenders routinely use  complex artificial intelligence algorithms to
determine who qualifies for loans global financial  markets are moved by decisions made by machines
analyzing huge amounts of data in ways even  their programmers don't always understand
harare says the countries and companies that  control the most data will in the future be the
ones that control the world today in the world  data is worth much more than money 10 years ago
you had these big corporations paying billions  and billions for whatsapp for instagram and people
wondered are they crazy why do they pay billions  to get this application that doesn't produce any
money and the reason why because it produced data  and data is the key the world is increasingly kind
of cut up into spheres of of of data collection  of data harvesting uh in the cold war you had the
iron curtain now we have the silicon curtain  between the usa and china and where does the
data go california or does it go to shenzhen and  to shanghai into beijing harare is concerned the
pandemic has opened the door for more intrusive  kinds of data collection including biometric data
what is biometric data it's data about what's  happening inside my body what we've seen so far
it's corporations and governments collecting data  about where we go who we meet what movies we watch
the next phase is the surveillance going under  our skin i'm wearing a like a tracker that tracks
my heart rate my sleep i don't know where that  information is going where are the kgb agent on
your wrist willingly and i think it's benefiting  me and it is benefiting i mean the whole thing is
that it's not just dystopian it's also utopian  i mean this kind of data can also enable us to
create the best healthcare system in history the  question is what else is being done with that data
and who supervises it who regulates it earlier  this year the israeli government gave its citizens
health data to pfizer to get priority access to  their vaccine the data did not include individual
citizens identities so what does pfizer want the  data of all israelis for because to develop new
medicines new treatments you need the medical data  increasingly that's the basis for how for medical
research and of course it's not all bad harare  has been criticized for pointing out problems
without offering solutions but he does have  some ideas about how to limit the misuse of data
one key rule is that if you get my  data the data should be used to help me
and not to manipulate me another key rule that  whenever you increase surveillance of individuals
you should simultaneously increase surveillance  of the corporation and governments and the people
at the top and the third principle is that never  allow all the data to be concentrated in one place
that's the recipe for a dictatorship netflix tells  us what to watch and amazon tells us what to buy
eventually within 10 or 20 or 30 years such  algorithms could also tell you what to study
at college and where to work and whom to marry and  even whom to vote for without greater regulation
harare believes we're at risk of becoming  what he calls hacked humans what does that
mean to hack a human being is to get to know  that person better than they know themselves
and based on that to increasingly manipulate  you this outside system it has the potential
to remember everything everything you ever did  and uh to analyze and find patterns in this data
and to get a much better idea of who you  really are i came out as gay when i was 21
it should have been obvious to me when i was 15  that i'm gay but something in the mind blocked it
now if you think about a teenager today facebook  can know that they are gay or amazon can know that
they are gay long before they do just based on  analyzing patterns and based on that you can tell
somebody's sexual orientation completely and what  does it mean if you live in iran or if you live
in russia or in some other homophobic country  and the police know that you're gay even before
you know it when people think about data they  think about companies finding out what their
likes and dislikes are but the data that you're  talking about it goes much deeper than that like
think in 20 years when the entire personal history  of every journalist every judge every politician
every military officer is held by somebody  in beijing or in washington your ability to
manipulate them is like nothing before in history  it's really good ferrari lives outside tel aviv
with his husband itsekyahav they've been together  for nearly 20 years it was yahov who read harare's
lecture notes for a history course and convinced  him to turn them into his first book sapiens
i read the lessons i couldn't stop talking  about it for me it was clear that it could be
a huge bestseller yahov is now hirari's agent  and together they started a company called
sapienship they're creating an interactive exhibit  that'll take visitors through the history of human
evolution and challenge them to think about the  future of mankind harare also just published the
second installment of a graphic novel based on  sapience and he's teaching courses at israel's
hebrew university in ethics and philosophy  for computer scientists and bioengineers
when people write code they are reshaping  politics and economics and ethics and the
structure of human society when i think of coders  and engineers i don't think of philosophers and
poets it's not the case now but it should  be the case because they are increasingly
solving philosophical and poetical riddles if  you're designing you know a self-driving car
so the self-driving car will  need to make ethical decisions
like suddenly a kid jumps in front of the car and  the only way to to to prevent running over the kid
is to swerve to the side and be hit by a truck  and your own owner who is asleep in the back seat
will might be killed you need to tell the  algorithm what to do in this situation
so you need to actually solve the  philosophical question who to kill
last month the united nations suggested a  moratorium on artificial intelligence systems that
seriously threaten human rights until safeguards  are agreed upon and advisers to president biden
are proposing what they call a bill of rights to  guard against some of the new technologies harori
says just as homo sapiens learned to cooperate  with each other many thousands of years ago
we need to cooperate now certainly now we are  at the point when we need global cooperation
you cannot regulate the explosive power of  artificial intelligence on a national level
i'm not trying to kind of prophesy what will  happen i'm trying to warn people about the most
dangerous possibilities in the hope that we  will do something in the present to prevent them